This course is going
to be running the 13th through
the 17th, Monday through
Friday mornings and afternoons.
What we're going to
be doing is something
that is a little bit
terrifying, which
is attempting to
teach Introduction
to Computational Neuroscience
using a tool that has only very
recently been developed.
Only in the last
couple of years
have we been actually
developing Neuroblox.
We have a beta
version that is now
being released as of this week.
And so you are actually
the first users
who are not the people
who develop the software.
That is kind of
exciting, but also runs
the risk that there may be
bugs that we hadn't anticipated
because you will use the
software in ways that we hadn't
anticipated.
That's all a good thing.
And so rather than fighting
it, I suggest we embrace it.
There is within the
Slack in #general
bookmarked a reported bug.
There's a
difference between I'm
trying to do something and
I don't know how to do it,
versus I know how to do
it and it's not working.
If it's the latter, then
please report the bug so
that we can try to rectify
it as soon as possible.
This is our team.
As you can see, it's
pretty interdisciplinary.
It's also across
multiple institutions.
MIT is obviously very
well represented here.
Members of this team
are going to be some
of them are physically here.
Some of them are monitoring
channels remotely.
But this gives you sort of an
idea of who the main individuals
are so that when I credit
them during the talk,
you kind of understand
who they are.
And this also gives
you a sense of who would
be answering your questions.
If we're going to talk about
Intro to Computational Modeling,
OK, so what is
computational modeling?
Modeling means different
things to different people.
If we're thinking about
a material model--
the father of cybernetics
had a very memorable statement.
"The best material model of a
cat is another or preferably
the same cat."
What does that mean?
It means that if you
want to characterize
all of the features of
a particular system,
your model must be--
essentially, have a
one-to-one mapping
between the features
you're trying to describe
and the components of the model.
But Lemma's point here--
Lemma is the cat, our cat.
Her point is that you run
the risk of overfitting,
depending on what the
aims of the model are.
So if your aim is to answer
every possible question,
then you need to essentially
reproduce the system completely.
But in most cases, we
make strategic choices
about what we're trying to
accomplish with the model.
And so Lemma says, "a
computational model's level
of resolution is a
critical design choice
that needs to match
the system's goals."
I agree with her.
She's a smart cat.
Different computational
neuroscience software platforms
exist.
Some of them are
very well developed
and have accomplished
a tremendous amount.
Neuroblox distinguishes
itself by its specific set
of goals, which is
really optimized
for biomedical
engineering applications.
What we're
primarily interested in
is mechanistic integration of
disorder and treatment-relevant
targets.
And that motivation is informing
all the design decisions
that we made in terms of the
architecture of the software,
what we leave in, what we leave
out, what types of solvers
we use.
All sorts of technical and
also conceptual decisions
are based on that.
If we think about
where our data come from,
they could come all the
way from the bottom patch
clamp all the way to the
clinical signs and symptoms
that we're trying to explain,
so psychiatric and neurological
disorders.
And so you might be
able to ask, all right,
what is causing dementia?
What is the time
course of dementia?
Who is at risk for dementia?
What will be the progression
of that disorder?
Depression.
Addiction.
Many of these are disorders
that are not simply binary.
They have trajectories.
They might be cyclical,
like bipolar disorder.
They might be degenerative.
They might have an
onset, for example,
with psychotic disorders
that start in men at one age
and at women at another.
And you'd want to
understand why.
And so what we want
to do is to create
a model that is
capable of addressing
those sorts of questions.
In order to address
those sorts of questions,
we're going to have to ask
in terms of the modeling
level, what are the
targets potentially
at all scales that might give
rise to these emergent effects?
That means that
we're going to need
to be able to include
components within our model that
have something to do with ion
channels, receptors, neurons,
neural masses, brain regions,
all the way up to the circuits
that we associate with the
macroscopic neuroimaging world.
Ultimately, we output to
clinical signs and symptoms
everything from
behavioral outputs
in terms of how
someone might perform
on a task, but also
mood, for example,
if we want to chart
bipolar disorder.
What this means then is that
if the mechanistic targets are
at all of these
scales, the treatments
also might be operating
at many different scales.
So we want to be able
to, within our model,
implement different
pharmaceutical treatments
and ask, what would
be the impact of,
for example, in this
case, giving L-dopa?
We might want to
ask about metabolism
in the context of brain aging
and Alzheimer's disease,
where in general, the field
believes that metabolism has
a really critical role to play.
But what is the pathway by
which this metabolic dysfunction
actually then affects
brain function?
And specifically, why some brain
functions rather than others?
And then finally, we might want
to be able to ask of the model,
tell us something about what
happens when we stimulate
the system in various ways.
So if we administer
deep brain stimulation
or transcranial
magnetic stimulation,
we're influencing the system
in some particular way.
And bear in mind
that the influence,
the direction of influence
is not just upward.
There are also
feedback effects that
are working downwards as well.
So we need to consider the
causality from the bottom layer
all the way to the top
layer, but then also,
how elements of the top
layer feed back down
to the bottom layer.
The final point
I want to mention
is that if, in
fact, what we want
to get out of this is something
like homeostatic regulation
or behavior on a behavioral
task, then our outputs have to,
in some sense, they have
to be able to do a task.
The model needs to
be able to do a task.
It needs to not just say,
this person will do it well,
this person will not do it well.
We want the model to actually
elicit the task behavior
that a human would perform.
So that imposes all
sorts of constraints.
But it's good, and
actually I would
say critical, to have those
ends in mind before you start.
I should also mention that a
lot of the models that you're
going to be working with
don't take advantage
of all the capabilities
we're developing,
because as an introduction to
computational neuroscience, what
we're trying to do is to show
you how the tool can be used
with existing models, which are
canonical and very important
within the field.
And then we'll
give you an example
of how Neuroblox can be applied
to the sorts of models
that we're describing here.
In the world of neuroimaging,
which is where I come from,
there are terms that get
tossed around a lot: "networks",
"circuits", "computational model".
And that's true.
I mean, these are real entities.
These are important
areas of research
that have yielded really
important insights.
But different fields
have different ways
of understanding the same words.
And so for the
sake of clarity, I
want to be kind of
clear about what
we mean by these
things in this context.
In the context
of neuroimaging,
when we say "networks", and
even sometimes "circuits",
what is typically
meant is something
that looks like this, where
we have a seed region,
and then we're asking, what
other areas of the brain
are co-activated with
that seed region?
So what we're really doing
is taking a time series
from one region and asking
for the time series that
are obtained from every
other voxel in the brain
or every other
region in the brain,
depending on how you
parsellate your brain.
The areas that are associated
with that first region that
are somehow connected or
communicating or signaling
are described in that way based
on correlation coefficients.
You can also expand this to
a general linear model, where
you have a design
matrix and you ask,
in response to some particular
experimental input: what areas
are activated in response to
that input, differentially,
let's say, between one
condition versus another,
between one population
versus another?
But these are all
statistical tests.
When we talk about computational
modeling or computational
neuroscience within the
neuroimaging world, what
is often meant is
really something very,
very different than how basic
neuroscientists would think
of computational neuroscience.
What's happening [in neuroimaging] is that
there is an emphasis, really,
on developing tools
that are able to make
better use of the
time series that
are obtained from these voxels.
The sorts of
computational tools that
have been developed
in neuroimaging,
by and large (there
are exceptions),
really, they hinge around
two different concepts.
One is improving reliability and
reproducibility of connectivity,
which as we said,
are correlations,
co-activation patterns,
which are described
through the general linear
model, or feature extraction,
often through
independent components
analysis using meta analyses
across data sets and modalities.
Given what has
sometimes been described
as a reproducibility crisis
within the fMRI world,
there's a very strong
effort to see, OK,
if we say these networks
exist for one data set,
do they also exist
for other data sets?
If we say they exist
for fMRI, can we
elicit them also from MEG?
So the idea here is really
to use computational power
to enhance this reproducibility
and reliability.
The second context
is using some methods
from machine learning to
decode functions and disorders
from time series.
And in this case,
what's really happening
is that people are identifying
signatures, brain signatures,
for this disorder
versus that disorder,
or for this function
versus that function.
And here, the advantage
is that decoding actually
can be done not
just on time series,
but on lots of
different types of data.
So you can use multimodal data
and use structural information,
functional information,
all sorts of information
together to provide these
sorts of diagnostic tools.
But for the purposes of what
I've said in terms of our aims,
those two approaches
are not what we mean
by computational neuroscience.
For one thing,
what we need is
to be able to simulate
the impact of one drug
or device versus another,
to tune parameters
and ask how the system will
change, to ask how a patient who
has undergone deep
brain stimulation
is likely to respond
to tuning parameters
this way versus that way.
All of this requires simulation.
This requires an
element of time.
So it's not just asking:
are you in this category
or this category?
It's asking: how does the
system evolve over time?
Both of these methods
that I've described
are discriminative.
You can't simulate with them.
You can describe symptoms.
You can describe disorders.
You can describe functions.
But what you can't
do is simulate
how they will evolve over time.
In terms of interpretability,
machine learning
has its strengths precisely
because it's high dimensional
in this context.
There are types of
machine learning,
of course, that are generative.
But that's not what's
being generally applied
to neuroimaging data.
But because it's
high dimensional,
the flip side to that is
that it's not interpretable.
So you can't take those
signatures elicited
by machine learning
from neuroimaging data
and then reverse engineer what
actually the brain is doing.
Likewise, using multiple
pairwise correlations
to infer circuit architecture
is not very reliable
when you're looking at networks.
For one thing,
circuits include feedback,
and correlations fall
apart when you're
looking at systems
that include feedback.
The second point is
that in a network,
you have pairwise
correlations, which
if you add them-- so if you have
a particular network with nodes
and you ask, what's the
correlation between this node
and this node, and then
this node and this node,
and this node and this node, the
error estimates for each edge
multiply.
And as a result,
when you ask, what
is the error of a
single connection,
the error for a
single connection
might be totally manageable.
But once you get to a
network with many edges,
you have this exponential
amplification of error.
It can very quickly
get out of control.
And actually, if you start
with an R value, so a Pearson
correlation of
0.45, which is quite
strong within
neuroimaging, you'd
be super happy if you
got such a correlation.
But that's only explaining
20% of the variance, which
means 80% of the variance
is not being explained.
Now, if you have
three steps, you
have 0.2 cubed, which means
that you're not explaining
over 99% of the variance.
That's not a very good model.
So for that reason,
it's not a great way
to identify the
structure of circuits.
The other problem
is that even if you
were doing a great job
of absolutely identifying
the structure of the
circuit with your networks,
the other issue is
that just talking
about who's connected
to whom is a very
sparse amount of information
about the structure
of your model.
And so as we'll
see, there are a lot
of functions, really critical
functions within the brain, that
require a lot more information
than who is talking to whom.
So if that's not
what we're using,
if we're not going to be
just relying on connectivity,
connectivity understood as
correlation coefficients
or general linear models,
then what we'll be using
is something called
dynamical systems,
which are based on ODE systems.
The advantage
of ODE systems is
that they address a lot of the
concerns that I just raised.
You can talk about the
error of the system
as a whole in a way that
you can't with a series
of correlations.
You can model
explicitly feedback
and also, you can simulate.
And so here, I take as a really
simple example glucose insulin
regulation.
This is something that
probably all of you know about.
You eat a cookie.
Your glucose levels go up.
But glucose levels being
too high is quite dangerous.
And so your endocrine system
has a feedback loop that
allows you to release insulin.
Insulin then lowers
your glucose levels.
If your glucose levels go too
low, then you release glucagon
and the glucose levels go up.
So here you have a
homeostatic regulatory system
that maintains glucose within
appropriate thresholds.
And so what you can see here
is if we give a glucose bolus,
we can simulate how glucose
and insulin will respond.
So glucose will respond first.
Insulin will respond
shortly thereafter.
And then glucose will go down.
And then insulin will go down.
You can see that one of the nice
features of this kind of model
is that if we say that the
circuit is dysregulated,
we can be kind of precise
about how it gets dysregulated.
And it turns out
that different ways
of dysregulating
the same circuit
will lead to very
different phenotypes.
In Type 1 diabetes,
unmedicated Type 1 diabetics
tend to be very, very
thin because insulin
is responsible for putting
on body fat and storing it.
Type 2 diabetics
who are unmedicated
will tend to be
overweight because they
have too much insulin, and
they're storing the glucose
rather than consuming it.
So if you were to just look at
individuals with Type 1 and Type
2 diabetes and just look
at those phenotypes,
you wouldn't
necessarily understand
that those two disorders,
which look completely different
from a clinical
perspective, actually
represent different
types of dysregulation
of the very same circuit.
That is actually
kind of provocative
when we think about
psychiatric disorders,
because psychiatric
disorders tend
to implicate many of the same
circuits, in spite of the fact
that [their clinical presentations] can look
quite different.
And so this provides
a way of thinking
for how that might occur.
Importantly, also, I've just
done a hypothetical experiment
here.
I've given glucose.
I've seen how there's
a response over time.
But what's very nice about
being able to simulate
is I can ask, all right,
if we chronically do this,
how will the system
change over time?
We can ask about
longer term trajectories.
So when we do
experiments in the lab,
whether we're doing
it in the scanner
or we're doing it with
electrophysiology,
we have a very small
time window in which
we can conduct our experiments.
But clinically, disorders,
diseases, they evolve sometimes
over decades.
And so understanding
how that process occurs
is something that we
can do with simulations.
One example here is
with Type 2 diabetes.
If there's a chronically
elevated demand for insulin,
beta cells hit their
carrying capacity.
After a certain point, the
beta cells, they're fatigued.
They can't keep up
with the demand.
And as a result, Type 2
diabetics can also become Type
1-like diabetics.
Again, this provides
a way of thinking
about certain types of
psychiatric disorders
that seem to flip states,
so for example, from mania
to depression, all sorts
of states from anxiety
to depression.
There are all sorts
of trajectory changes
that occur over much
longer periods of time
than you can measure
in a laboratory
that you'd want to
be able to explain
with your computational models.
And note that when I
say carrying capacity,
in the context of neuroscience,
this is a very real concern,
because a lot of
these dysregulations
are putting a tremendous amount
of excess stress on the system.
And so if you are in a state,
like mania, where you're rapidly
depleting dopamine, then
what you're going to do
is to put a lot of stress
on precursors for dopamine,
like tyrosine, for example,
where acetylcholine
has a precursor choline.
And what can happen is that as
you hit that carrying capacity,
the system can collapse.
This is a really important
dynamic, overshoot and collapse,
that you'll want to be keeping
in mind for the models.
Finally, I just want to
really bring home, again,
the idea that what I've just
described, the story of being
able to regulate between
glucose and insulin
and to be able to dysregulate in
more than one way, none of this
can be captured
through just asking,
who is connected to whom?
So if we want to
ask, all right, well,
I said, it's not just about
excitatory and inhibitory
responses.
We might need more structure.
So here's an example of this
kind of modeling applied
to the neuroimaging scale.
And we can look at this
prefrontal limbic circuit.
Again, there are
many similarities
with what we've just seen
between the glucose insulin
regulation.
One of them is that we
have not one feedback loop,
but multiple feedback
loops that are all
interacting with one another.
And that's one reason why you
need to simulate the results,
because these are complex
enough that you can't just
imagine, well, if I were
to do this, this would happen,
if I were to do that,
this would happen.
These are feedback
loops that are
operating at multiple scales.
So, at the bottom scale
affecting the top scale.
But also, at each scale you
have multiple feedback loops
interacting with each other.
I also want to point
out that one feature
of this particular model is the
importance of gating mechanisms.
There are several
gating mechanisms here.
One is the thalamus, which is
important for sensory gating,
but also through the IFG in
terms of other types of gating,
determining whether
there's object recognition
or not, and that
affects the feedback
through the ventral stream.
Having these gating
mechanisms, thresholds,
and also timing
issues, the question
of whether some signals are
faster or slower than others
is going to affect
the dynamics as well.
This is something, again,
that ODE systems can provide.
So like Type 1 and
Type 2 diabetics,
depending on how the
system disregulates,
determines the output
in terms of behavior.
Here we were looking
at a largish sample
of 256 individuals: all
the way from clinically
anxious to clinically reckless
and everything in between,
and seeing if we could
map where on the spectrum
someone would lie based on the
particular type of dysregulation
and its degree.
Now, what I just showed you
should be a little bit--
this should shock you a
little bit because I just
talked about gating mechanisms.
And yet, this model,
it has filters.
It has comparators.
It has gains and so forth.
And for those of you
who are neuroscientists,
you are probably asking,
well, wait a second.
I mean, does the brain really
have comparators and gains?
And is that real?
Or is that just a way to
make the simulation work?
This is exactly
the question that we
want to be able to address.
So the question really is, what
are the computational primitives
of brain circuits?
When we say that the
brain is "processing",
what is doing the processing?
Again, it's not just that
this is connected to this
and this is connected to that.
That's not going to
process anything.
So what is doing
that processing?
In the case of an
electrical circuit,
we know what those
computational primitives are.
These are synthetic circuits.
We have capacitors.
We have gains.
We have resistors and so forth.
And so the question
is, even though
in computational
neuroscience sometimes
we use analogs for
those, we'd like
to know that those analogs have
an actual underlying biological
basis.
In Neuroblox,
those are represented.
These underlying processing
elements at the bottom scale
are described as
computational primitives,
biomimetic
computational primitives
because they're meant to
reflect actual brain processes.
And here's an example
of one of them.
This is lateral inhibition.
And if you see how
this works, so you
have a number of
excitatory inputs.
And the first one that
hits inhibits the rest.
I just want to point
out something first.
Again, this is not just
who's connected to whom.
There's a critical timing issue.
The first one that
hits inhibits the rest.
So any model that doesn't
consider the timing element,
it would be missing something
critical about this function.
And second, this is acting
as a type of filter.
And depending on
how you tune it,
it can have different effects.
But it is one potential
mechanism for a filter.
So one of the tasks
that we've had
in Neuroblox is
figuring out, what
are these computational
primitives?
These computational
primitives are mostly
at the spiking neuron scale.
And they're really
micro assemblies.
They're very tiny
structures that have
a very particular function.
And the way we define them is
the smallest possible structure--
the smallest possible
structure that can
perform a particular function.
Here is a sample of these
potential computational
primitives.
These are not made
up out of our heads.
These are coming from
data, from the literature.
They need to be figured out.
And then from these
computational primitives,
we can arrange
these microcircuits
in ways that allow us to
design macro circuits.
So in other words, you have
a bunch of micro circuits
that arrange to create
a macro circuit.
Then that can be
treated as a block that
then is used to arrange
a larger macro circuit.
And this is how
Neuroblox grows in scale.
It's circuits of
circuits of circuits
of circuits all the way up.
Here's an example of
this particular circuit.
And as you can see, so this is
the corticostriatal circuit.
And it's doing a
particular task.
So you might recall that I
said that one of our desiderata
is we want our model to be
actually capable of producing
some effect.
So we want it to be
able to do a task.
And in this case, it's going
through a series of steps.
This is, again, all the way
starting from the spiking neuron
scale, all the way up
to what will be measured
with the local field
potential scale,
and then through
that to behavior.
So these different components
that were assembled
were assembled from
the literature.
So this is a kind
of an integration
of many, many decades
worth of experiments.
Data, models all got
normalized into this Neuroblox
type of nomenclature, and
then combined together
to create this comprehensive
corticostriatal model that
can do category learning.
We then independently
validated against
macaque electrophysiology.
Now again, the
only reason we can
do that is that it's
producing simulations,
so predicted outputs
as trajectories
at multiple scales, spiking
neuron, local field potential,
and behavioral.
And it's being checked and
validated at multiple scales
to make sure that this
is actually correct.
Now, this brings me
to the next question
which is, the user
experience, the GUI,
how do we interact with this?
What we want is,
again, to create
a tool for
neuroscientists, of course,
but also for neuroscience to be
actually extended to developing
better drugs and devices.
So that means that it
can't be the domain
of a small select group
of hard core computational
neuroscientists who live
in a cave somewhere.
It needs to be
something accessible
to many different types of
populations: experimentalists,
theoreticians, and so forth.
And so we really thought
this through very carefully,
again, with those aims in mind.
The tool that I
used with my team
to derive that
fMRI scale control
circuit for the
prefrontal limbic circuit
was done in Simulink.
But Simulink, it
was really developed
for electrical engineering.
It has computational
primitives that
are really specific to
electrical engineering, which
means that it has the advantage
of being able to allow you
to model in a graphical
way, which allows you to tap
into your intuitions, your
visual intuitions, about what
a circuit looks like.
It also allows you to
work at multiple scales,
so you can have blocks
within your Simulink
that are made up of other
circuits underneath it.
So it has many similarities
to what we're trying to do.
But again, this was
optimized specifically
for electrical engineering.
And we want to make sure
that the tool doesn't--
it's sort of optimized
for the sorts of questions
neuroscientists would want to
be asking and also, ideally
also keeps you from
making mistakes
that Simulink would
allow you to make simply
because it doesn't have
biological constraints built in.
So one of the practical problems
we ran into very quickly
is that when we're
looking at circuits
and if you want to map
this onto a brain, which
is the geography that
neuroscientists are
familiar with, the problem is
that circuits are usually not
all in one slice.
If we take one
particular slice,
we're going to have to
be a little bit loosey
goosey about putting the
blocks where they belong.
because we're going to
have cortical areas,
subcortical areas, the front,
the back, the side and side.
And so we had to
come up with a way
of doing this that would
allow the entire circuit
to be visible at once.
And so inspired by a Mercator
projection map, we thought, OK,
can we actually create a
flat map representation
of the entire brain?
And we were able to make
use of some wonderful work
by Hahn and Duckworth in
2023 that did exactly that.
And we were able
to adapt from this.
So here is the GUI
that Neuroblox uses.
And just to walk you
through how to work
your way through this GUI,
the blocks, which include
computational
primitives, but then
it also includes the blocks
that are these circuits that
are created, the
macro circuits that
are created from these
computational primitives.
And so then, again, the
blocks of blocks of blocks
can also be included
as blocks, which
means that when someone
creates a circuit,
they are using the same blocks.
The advantage also, by the way,
in having different groups work
from the same common
set of elements
is that it
accomplishes something
that all too often
doesn't happen
in computational neuroscience,
which is the ability
to compare one model to another
and to integrate models.
So computational
neuroscience tends
to be a very artisanal
activity, where every group has
its own ways of defining the
circuits and their interactions,
their interaction rules,
the ODE solvers even.
And so the advantage of having
this common set of elements that
can be combined is like
in electrical engineering,
if someone says resistor,
I know what resistor means.
I can change parameters
for the resistor.
I can create another
type of resistor.
But a resistor has
a common meaning,
where multiple
groups can combine
circuits, electrical
circuits, in meaningful ways.
But by the way, I should mention
you can create your own blocks.
It's not as if that you are
stuck with the blocks that
already are there.
You can use your own data
or other people's data
to create new blocks.
And then you have your blocks
are arranged on the brain.
So I don't know if you can
see, but these are actually
brain regions.
Can everybody see the brain?
Yeah.
So this is a flat brain that
includes different brain
regions.
And so you actually put your
block on the brain region.
If you select the brain
region, it will automatically
put the block where it belongs.
And the reason why we want to
put things where they belong
is partially because,
again, we have
as neuroscientists certain
intuitions about the brain,
right?
If we see something
in the visual cortex,
we know what that means.
If it's in the striatum,
So we want to have
things where they belong.
But there are also other
important advantages
of having there be a spatial
geography that is meaningful.
And one of them is
that you can actually
have mechanistic
maps that overlay
with this map, this brain.
And so if you have, for example,
you have different GLUT4 density
distributions
throughout the brain,
if you know what
the GLUT4 density
distribution is throughout the
brain, you can map it onto here.
And that will change the
underlying parameters
of how your model is running.
The last thing I just wanted to
point out is these connections.
So this is arranged on the left
between inputs and outputs.
So the inputs can be drugs,
devices, stimuli, anything
that is actually going
to go into the system.
And then you have
what comes out of it.
And so what comes
out of it could
be various ways of
visualizing your data,
but also, a motor
action, for example.
So if the simulation is
conducting a particular task
in response to some
particular type of stimulus,
the output would be
the behavioral output.
This is being
adapted to a couple
of different applications.
One of these is a Pharma Module.
One of the things we want
to be able to do is to ask,
if we have different
drugs, how are they
affecting not only
neurotransmitter levels,
but also receptor dynamics?
We need to be able to
model receptor dynamics.
It means that when you tag
a particular connection,
you will identify what
neurotransmitter that is.
And then you have
the opportunity
to include relevant
receptor dynamics.
Obviously, at this
level is going
to affect the
computational primitives,
which means that then those
computational primitives will
affect the running of
the circuit as a whole.
And so when you ask, what
is the impact of giving
this drug versus that drug,
at this dose versus that dose,
it's affecting this
level, which is then
going to be affecting the
computational primitives.
And then the
computational primitives
are going to have emergent
effects all the way up
to the behavioral scale.
We also have a Metabolic Module.
This is composed of metabolic
flux equations that,
for those of you who do
magnetic resonance spectroscopy,
allows you to ask, how
will changing metabolism
of this parameter
versus that parameter,
how will it change the behavior
of the system as a whole,
even at the level of
changing someone's diet,
putting someone in
ketosis versus not?
Giving someone Type
2 diabetes, how
is that going to
affect the entire--
so this will affect the
system, the metabolic system.
But then this outputs
neurotransmitters.
Again, those
neurotransmitters are
going to go into that circuit.
And then the circuit
will run its simulations
and have some output.
And that allows us to ask a
whole new category of questions
like, why is it that GLP1
agonists seem to curb addiction?
Well, in order to
answer that question,
we're going to need to be able
to model the metabolic system
and also ask how it impacts
the neural circuits, including
behavior.
And so one of the things
that we're very excited about
is the ability to not only
model circuits within the brain,
but also the brain's
interactions with other systems,
for example, the immune system.
If you've ever thought about
long COVID and its impact
on brain fog, again,
these are really
important clinical
questions to ask.
And then we have also a
Neuromodulation Module
in progress, where we're
interested in being
able to stimulate the
circuit in various ways
with DBS or transcranial
magnetic stimulation
and ask, OK, so how is this
affecting the system as a whole
and its behavior over time?
So finally, I want to say
that one of the grand goals
is to develop Neuroblox
as a knowledge integration
ecosystem in a way that I don't
see existing platforms have kind
of quite gotten us there yet.
And one of them really
has to do with allowing
for the ability of
community-based modeling,
where if one team
is contributing
data and another team
is contributing models
and another team is
contributing other models,
that there can be an integration
and comparison of the models
to the data, the models to
each other in a way, as I said,
that's only possible
if you're working
from a common set
of modular elements.
All of this gets
powered by Julia
and facilitated this
hosting for this week,
but probably also long-term
will be through JuliaHub.
Obviously, this is very
computationally expensive.
And so the
capabilities that Julia
offers in terms of high
performance computing
are really critical.
Neuroblox allows for
simulations and model fitting.
The modularity
that I've described
is designed from the
ground up for automating
a lot of the processes that
otherwise wouldn't be possible:
creating models,
testing models, fine tuning
models, parameter fitting,
comparison of models,
et cetera, global parameter
setting, so again,
putting together a whole
bunch of different models,
asking how they
integrate, and then being
able to change parameters
for the whole system
from one place, and model
comparison and integration.
And now, Helmut Strey, who's
our lead software engineer,
will take over.
I wanted to spend
a few more minutes
on the more technical
aspects of Neuroblox.
In particular, we want to
talk about why we chose Julia
over other [programming languages].
And to start, I
wanted to introduce
what is coined the
"two-language problem"
in computational science.
And that has to do with if you
want to do something performant,
you want to have a low-level
programming language that
is really fast, right?
And that's for execution
speed, because you don't really
want to have a slow simulation,
because typically, you
want to push the envelope.
But on the other hand, if you
have a lower level language,
it's very hard to develop code.
And to increase
development speed,
you need a higher
level language.
And so typically
what people do is,
and this is even true in
computational neuroscience,
is that typically, they use C or
C++ for really performant code,
and then maybe use Python to
interface with that C code.
There are libraries
that essentially
say, build me a neuron,
build me a neuron assembly,
and then that gets
translated into C.
So the nice thing is that
Julia actually solves
these two-language problems
because it is actually
the motto of Julia, is:
"Julia walks like Python
and runs like C." It's
a compiled language.
And it actually, if you
look at performance, there
are online Julia
performance benchmarks,
it's very much like
C, sometimes actually
will beat C in performance
because it's better optimized.
But that's the first thing.
That was our first decision.
The other decision is on
performance and accuracy
of simulation of
differential equations.
Julia, I think, has--
and I think it's pretty--
it's a true statement
that Julia probably
has the best performance
differential equation
solvers in the whole field,
and not only ODE solvers,
but also SDE solvers and delayed
differential equation solvers,
and actually also differential
algebraic equation solvers.
And here are some benchmarks
that I want to show you.
So these are non-stiff
solvers and stiff solvers.
And one of the things that
you will see immediately
is that Julia performs about
two orders of magnitude
faster than Python or Matlab,
which is not super surprising,
because Matlab and
Python are not very high
performance languages.
And they perform very,
very, almost equal
to any implementation
that you can do in C.
So this was one of the reasons.
I don't think there's
any other language that
has so many choices in solvers.
And that's one of
our motivations
that when people
use the software,
they can actually pick
the right solvers.
And this is why I'm actually
showing non-stiff versus stiff.
Non-stiff are
differential equations
where the functions
are relatively smooth
and nice and well-behaved.
And then you can essentially
work with adaptive solvers.
Stiff solvers are more
for hard problems,
like chaotic
systems, things that
are oscillating, for example,
highly nonlinear systems,
where you have to have different
strategies to solve differential
equations.
And you can actually read
this up on the benchmarks
here, down here.
The other thing that
we were very keen about
is differentiability.
Julia has a large, automated
differentiation ecosystem.
And I don't know
how many people have
heard of autodifferentiation.
Some of you.
So autodifferentiation, I
mean, you probably heard,
clearly heard from machine
learning and neural networks
that they call this
back propagation.
Back propagation is essentially
reverse autodifferentiation.
It's a different word.
Different fields
use different words,
but it's essentially
algorithmic, the same thing.
The reason why I think
it's important to say
automatic differentiation
is because there's also
forward automatic
differentiation, which
you use when you only
have about 100 parameters.
Then actually, forward
differentiation
is better than reverse
differentiation.
Reverse autodifferentiation
is really effective
when you have a
lot of parameters.
So for example, in
neural networks,
you have 10,000 or big models
have billions of parameters.
Then back propagation is
really the method to do.
And we have all these
libraries essentially
in Julia, where you can
apply autodifferentiation
to any function in Julia.
I mean, maybe not any function,
but any function that is--
it's like in math,
what is integrable
and what is differentiable,
sort of like kinds of things.
And the reason why we are so
excited about all the auto
differentiable is
because then you
can address problems that
you couldn't before address.
One of the things is, what do
you need differentiability for?
Optimization.
So for example, if you
have a wonderful model
that you just
discovered and vetted
and it's the best model
that you can come up with,
what you would like to do is to
then take data, patient data,
and then fit parameters
to that particular model.
And you can only do
this if you actually
are good at differentiation.
So optimization problem,
the inverse problem, that's
the parameter fitting problem.
And then there's
other applications
that we're actually
pursuing in Neuroblox.
And one is optimization
of the system itself.
So let's say you have a
collection of neurons.
You pick the neurons
because they are the ones
that you want to use.
But you need to optimize
them in terms of performance.
You want the right firing rate.
You want the right frequency
spectrum and stuff like this.
And so what we can do is we
can essentially put constraints
on the performance of
these collection of neurons
and then do an optimization
process through optimization
[INAUDIBLE].
The other thing that
you can think of
is then if you go
the Bayesian route,
the Bayesian route would mean
that we don't necessarily
do parameter fitting.
We don't want to
fit best parameters.
What we would like
to find the posterior
probability of the
parameters given the data.
Then you would go in
the Bayesian route.
And when the Bayesian
route, there's
a lot of packages that allow
you to do a Hamilton Monte Carlo
on probability distributions.
So that would give you the
full posterior probability
of your data.
So the other reason
why we picked Julia
is because of composability.
Julia has in part
of the suite of SciML
tools, scientific
machine learning tools,
has a package that's called
Modeling Toolkit, which
uses symbolic equations to form
differential equation systems,
ODE systems.
And I just want to give
you a quick example.
So these are actually
two blocks in Neuroblox.
Each block is defined by
a differential equation.
And you see there's a very
small junction in there,
within the sigmoid function.
There's a little
junction in here.
And what you can do is
you can take, for example,
the output of one
block and connect it
to the junction
of the other one.
And then you can connect
this x to the junction
of the other one.
And I indicated this
by these arrows.
And that's exactly actually, how
you will see this in the GUI.
Every arrow essentially means
that I connect an output of one
of the ODE systems to an input
of the other ODE systems.
And so what modeling
toolkit essentially does
is it takes all these equations
and then cleans them up.
It, for example,
removes the junctions.
It eliminates the junctions
because the junction
is a connection
and then turns that
into a function that then can
be solved with an ODE solver.
So this is full composability.
And so the way we
constructed or designed
Neuroblox is by using a
hierarchical and composable
structure.
So for example, you start
with a Hodgkin-Huxley neuron.
You put five of those
or six of those neurons
together into what we call
a winner takes all circuit.
Actually, Lily was talking
about that exact circuit.
And then you can take all
these winner takes all circuits
and put them together and make,
for example, a cortical region
and assemble them.
Now, the nice thing about
this hierarchical structure
is that you also have
hierarchical namespace.
So if I have a
cortical region, I
can ask, so give
me the first winner
takes all circuit within
the cortical region
and then give me the second
excitatory neuron in that.
And that's essentially
a namespace
that you can walk through.
And I think in the
tutorials we will
see exactly how to use this.
We can also have
shared parameters.
So you could, for example,
say we'll do a cortical region
and all the parameters of
all the neurons are the same
and they are one number.
And then you can tune that
number rather than having
to tune 5,000
parameters at once.
We can also actually
define observables.
So we can put in
functions that then
can be later after
the simulation be
extracted from the system.
And actually, this is something
that Haris developed.
We have connection rules.
So if you have blocks and
you have other blocks,
then you can
essentially create rules
how to connect one
block to another block.
And it's very flexible.
And you will actually
learn during the tutorial,
I think, to make your own
blocks and your own connectors.
It's going to be
quite fun, actually.
I want to talk a little bit
about Neuroblox performance.
When we first
started this project,
we noticed that because we
start with symbolic equations,
it actually gets really slow.
So when you build
big systems, there's
a lot of simplifications
that has to be done.
And modeling
toolkit was actually
not up to the task to
give us fast compilation.
So what we noticed
actually that when
we have really large systems,
fully connected systems,
then the compilation
time is much larger
than the execution time.
And that's really bad.
So actually, Mason
was the driving force.
He developed a new way of
creating ODE systems, where
we take advantage of the fact
that we have the same thing
over and over.
So we have a
neuron, for example.
The neuron rules of connections
are always the same.
And then you can
essentially take
advantage of that structure.
Actually, what
really would we take
advantage of is that every
system that we create
is actually a graph,
because you have nodes.
You have edges and the edges
define the connections.
And creating equations out of
graphs is much more effective.
And so we created actually
a library: Graph Dynamics,
that compiles graph systems
much more efficiently.
And you can see Modeling
Toolkit is on the-- this
is the blue graph, blue data.
And Graph Dynamics is red.
And so we are, again,
orders of magnitude
faster than that
modeling toolkit.
And I conclude by saying
that we essentially
have the following features.
We are composable, hierarchical.
We can build neuroscience models
from computational primitives.
We have a native high
performance computing language.
I mean, Julia-- by the
way, I didn't say this.
Julia is about 10 years old.
It was developed here at MIT in
the math and computer science
department.
And it's actually a
language from mathematicians
for mathematicians.
But engineers can also use it.
It's, I think, fine.
But it's designed for high
performance computing,
so interface with GPUs
and multi-core CPUs.
By the way, JuliaHub is a way
of running Julia in the cloud.
And you can throw essentially
any computing power
on your problem.
So we have differential models
for optimization parameter
fitting.
That also then allows us to do
computational model comparisons,
because if you have two models,
they're all differentiable
and we can do parameter fitting,
then you can essentially
do Bayesian posterior ratios.
And then you can essentially
tell which model is better.
And that's actually one
of our plans in Neuroblox
that we could essentially have
people submit different models
and then we can rank them.
We can say, OK, so how well
do they do with respect
to the data that are available?
And so we also will have a
graphic user interface, which I
will present right after this.
Thank you so much.